Alright, בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. We are today on דף י', Daf
Yud, still a little behind, more than a little. Anyway, we are
picking up from the second wide line on י' עמוד א', Yud
Amud Aleph, two dots. אמר רבי יוחנן משום רבי שמעון בר יוחאי,
Amar Rabbi Yochanan mishum Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai, so says Rabbi Yochanan
in the name of Rabbi Shimon ben
Yochai, מאי דכתיב, mai dechtiv, what's meant by the פסוק pasuk פיה
פתחה בחכמה ותורת חסד על לשונה? piha patcha bechochma vetorat chesed al
leshona? So her mouth opens up with wisdom and the teaching of
kindness is on her tongue. So כנגד מי אמר שלמה מקרא זה?
keneged mi amar Shlomo mikra zeh? Opposite who did Shlomo say this
פסוק? pasuk? Because obviously he's not meaning not opposite a woman in
general, in general חז"ל Chazal understand that אשת חיל Eishet Chayil or
often understand that it's a metaphor for
תורה. Torah. Anyway, that the תורה Torah is the woman here being
praised. Anyway, according opposite what the תורה Torah did Shlomo say this
פסוק? pasuk? לא אמרה אלא כנגד דוד אביו, lo amrah ela keneged
David aviv, opposite David. Now this is tying into the fact that
we've been dealing with דרשות drashot of יתמו חטאים מן הארץ yitamu
chataim min haaretz which we will get back to. So he said
it's corresponding to David his father. שדר בחמישה עולמים ואמר שירה, shedar
bechamisha olamim veamar shirah, he lived in five worlds and he said
שירה shirah about each one of them.
דר במעי אמו ואמר שירה, dar bemei imo veamar shirah, he was
in his mother's womb and he said שירה. shirah. Now the מהרש"א
Maharsha actually says we don't literally mean that he was saying שירה
shirah at this time, that when he finally said שירה shirah later
in his life, it was reflecting the experience of these five times.
So one was the time in his mother's womb, שנאמר sheneemar ברכי
נפשי את ה' וכל קרבי את שם קדשו, barchi nafshi et Hashem
vechol kravai et shem kodsho, that my soul praise God and all
my inners His holy name. So inners in the sense of being
inside and in the mother's womb. יצא לאויר העולם, yatza laavir haolam,
this is all going to be an extended דרשה drasha of תהלים
Tehillim ק"ג kuf gimmel and ק"ד. kuf daled. He also mentioned תהלים
Tehillim ק"ד kuf daled before if you might remember, יתמו חטאים מן
הארץ yitamu chataim min haaretz and so on. So anyway, so that
was when he was in his mother's womb presumably praising the wonders
of creation that an infant can gestate and live in the mother's
womb. So that was number one. יצא לאויר העולם, yatza laavir haolam,
he comes out to the world והסתכל בכוכבים, vehistakel bakochavim, he saw
the stars ומזלות umazalot and the constellations or whatever ואמר שירה, veamar
shirah, שנאמר sheneemar ברכו ה' מלאכיו גבורי כח עושי דברו לשמוע בקול
דברו ברכו ה' כל צבאיו, barchu Hashem malachav giborei koach osei dvaro
lishmoa bekol dvaro barchu Hashem kol tzevaav, praise God His angels those
who do God's work,
praise God all of His host, all of the constellations.
So presumably the sense of like the wonder of the world of
the infant just being born.
So that's number two. ינק משדי אמו, yanak mishedei imo, he suckled
from his mother's breasts והסתכל בדדיה, vehistakel bedadeha, interestingly looked at her
breasts ואמר שירה, veamar shirah, שנאמר sheneemar ברכי נפשי את ה', barchi
nafshi et Hashem, let my soul praise God. All this is in
תהלים Tehillim ק"ג, kuf gimmel, some of the פסוקים psukim are a
little out of order but they're being reordered in order to have
this sequence. אל תשכחי כל גמוליו, al tishkechi kol gmulav, that I
shall not forget all of all that God has done for me.
Now גמול, gmul, like יגמל, yigamel, although interestingly because יגמל yigamel means
to be weaned, but we actually do that sometimes in English as
well, we say weaned when we actually mean suckled, like he was
weaned on so and so, we actually mean he was suckled on
so and so, not weaned, weaned means separated. But anyway here too
somehow they understand the word גומל gomel to mean to be sort
of nurtured and suckled and so on. So therefore that is the
second thing he is saying שירה shirah for now third, excuse me,
now what might that be about? You might think it's basically that
God creates people that they can nurture, women nurture their children, that
it's a natural part of human biology. But let's see what the
גמרא Gemara does with it.
מאי כל גמוליו? mai kol gmulav? What is meant by that
פסוק? pasuk? אמר רבי אבהו Amar Rabbi Abahu שעשה לה דדים במקום
בינה, sheasah lah dadim bimkom bina, that God made for the women
breasts in the place of understanding, in the heart right? Because the
גמרא Gemara very actually talks about בינה יתירה נתנה באשה, bina yeteira
nitna baishah, that the woman has special understanding and the heart as
the place of understanding. טעמא מאי? taama mai? What's the reason that
that's where they're located? אמר רב יהודה Amar Rav Yehuda כדי שלא
יסתכל במקום ערוה, kedei shelo yistakel bimkom ervah,
that the infant when suckling should not look at his mother's pubic
area, so you have the breasts there to sort of block it,
which is interesting. רב מתנא אמר Rav Matna amar כדי שלא יינק
ממקום הטינופת, kedei shelo yinakh mimkom hatinofet, that he should not suckle
from the place of filth, presumably that often what's referred to when
it's as a euphemism, not much of a euphemism, for the genital
area. So that's why God separated as it were the genitals from
the breasts from the genitals.
I don't learn from there.
I don't really know what to tell you about this, making a
sudden shift from the wonder of the human body to be able
to sort of provide for the nutrients
and to nurture the child to this type of an issue about
like
which is negative.
Which is negative, well certainly the מקום טינופת makom tinofet is negative.
I'm not sure what to do with the first answer about the
place of understanding.
No, its breasts so they cover up as they, they cover, right,
right,
right, right, both of those. No, it addresses the cover up and
say a... To cover, right, right, right
there,
right,
both of those you're right. The first explanation that it's somehow from
the place of understanding מקום בינה, makom binah, I mean again that's
a little strange, but at least there's some sense there that the
mother is, you know, through the milk imparting not just nutrients but
wisdom, understanding into the child. I mean I think if you took
that on its own terms, it could be framed very positively.
Oh, instead of במקום. bimkom.
Oh, instead... oh that's interesting. Also, that that's sort of like emphasizing
the physical providing rather than the instead of, instead of, as opposed
to in the place of, in the location of, you're saying instead
of. Interesting. Certainly the way the גמרא Gemara shifted it definitely. I
don't know if in the first statement it was that way.
I've seen the series is the ברכי Barchi also, right? Because that's
what everything is here. ברכי נפשי. Barchi nafshi. Right, right, absolutely.
It's all the ברכי, Barchi, ברכי, Barchi, ברכי. Barchi. Yeah, Michael's absolutely
correct, we're doing... we're fo... what? what?
But later it says במקום ערותה bimkom ervasoh so it's probably במקום
bimkom not במקום? bimkom?
Yeah, in the place of. Right. Yeah, I think clearly the first
statement of רבי אבהו Rabbi Abbahu was a positive one, that it's
somehow that it's like, you know, you're providing the nurture and the
physical nutrient and it's also type of an imparting of wisdom and
so on, but then it switches it very drastically. That is true.
Okay, and Michael's, yes, correct, pointing out that the point here is
sort of the ברכי, Barchi, ברכי, Barchi, ברכי, Barchi, doing a דרשה
drasha on each one of those five. So that's number three.
Now, where are we? רבה מפלתן של
רשעים Raba mapalsan she-rasha'im saw the downfall of the wicked and he
praised God, שנאמר יתמו חטאים מן הארץ ורשעים עוד אינם. she-ne'emar yitamu
chata'im min ha-aretz u-resha'im od enam.
So that was the פסוק pasuk we had been dealing with yesterday.
Let the wicked cease from the world and the, you know, and
the evil-doers are no longer. Not reading it like ברוריה, Beruriah, that
it's just the end of sin, but the end of sinners. ברכי
נפשי את ה' הללויה, Barchi nafshi es Hashem Halleluka,
let my soul praise God, praise God. ונסתכל ביום המיתה, v'histakel b'yom
hamisah,
the day of death, that's interesting, ואמר שירה. v'amar shira. שנאמר ברכי
נפשי את ה' ה' אלהי גדלת מאד. she-ne'emar Barchi nafshi es Hashem,
Hashem Elokai gadalta me'od. Hashem,
my God, you have been exceedingly great. הוד והדר לבשת, hod v'hadar
lavashta, you have cloaked yourself in majesty and glory. מאי משמע דיום
מיתה נאמר? mai mashma de-yom misa ne'emar? Where do you get a
sense that that's talking about the day of death? אמר רבה בר
שילה מסיפא דענינא דכתיב amar Rabbah bar Shila misafa de-inyana de-chsiv from
the end of the פסוק pasuk it says, like ברוריה, Beruriah, you
know, שפיל לסיפא דקרא. shfale de-seifa de-kra. So go look at the
end. תסתיר פניך יבהלון, tastir panecha yibaheyun, hide your face and they
will be confounded. תוסף רוחם יגועון, tosef rucham yigva'un,
you will gather up their spirit and they will expire. And what
exactly is the שירה shira of the יום המיתה? yom hamisah? First
of all it's quite fascinating that there's no שירה shira here for
the, the lived life in the middle, right? The שירה shira is
being gestated, born, and being sort of nursed and suckling, and then,
being killed and dying. So what about the שירה shira for the
maybe the life in the middle is very challenging, so I don't
know. But anyway, so יום המיתה yom hamisah is interesting, it could
be someone wants to sort of reframe this and it really means
the ultimate תחיית המתים techiyas hamaysim that comes after the יום המיתה.
yom hamisah. But you know, it could actually be, you know, that
there's actually a beautiful מדרש Midrash that says that, what was it?
I'm trying to remember, it's a מדרש תנחומא Midrash Tanchuma about how
somebody was... was it יצחק Yitzchak was מתפלל mispallel that there was
no sickness in the world? Until like יצחק... Yitzchak...
and יעקב, Yaakov, until there was חולשא? chulsha?
יעקב? Yaakov? Well יצחק Yitzchak it says he got old, maybe there
was the effects of old age. Was it יעקב Yaakov or יצחק?
Yitzchak? It was יעקב? Yaakov? Okay. So anyway, but the point that,
you know, that there's... we certainly value... I mean that sort of
also speaking about the power of sort of being able to transition,
you know, prepare oneself for death and transition and understand... anyway, that's
a separate related but separate discussion. Anyway, but the fact that, you
know, when there's death, we also tend to value life more. And
the preciousness of life is its own recognizing that ultimately, you know,
that there will be... that there will be death, although obviously it's
an evil, but there's also something about that that makes every moment
of life more precious. So that's I think a very different way
of reading this גמרא. Gemara. What does it mean he's praising God
for the day of death? But, but others try to just make
it more obviously positive and focus like I said on the תחיית
המתים, techiyas hamaysim, which is now what is being said explicitly here.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues, says the following.
Where were we?
Now we're still on this... we're still on this extended דרשה drasha
of יתמו חטאים מן הארץ yitamu chata'im min ha-aretz the ברכי נפשיס,
Barchi Nafshis, let's take a look. דרבי שמעון בר עקבא ואמרי לה
מר עקבא. de-Rabbi Shimon bar Ukva v'amrei lei Mar Ukva. So either
רבי שמעון בר עקבא Rabbi Shimon bar Ukva or מר עקבא Mar
Ukva הוה שכיח קמיה דרבי שמעון בן פזי, hava shchi'ach kamei de-Rabbi
Shimon ben Pazi, he used to be very frequented in front of
רבי שמעון בן פזי. Rabbi Shimon ben Pazi. והוה מסדר אגדתא קמיה
דרבי יהושע בן לוי. v'hava mesader agadta kamei de-Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi.
Now רבי שמעון בן פזי Rabbi Shimon ben Pazi was the one
who would sort of arrange the אגדתא agadta for רבי יהושע בן
לוי. Rabbi Joshua ben Levi. So he was like the Agadic master
of רבי יהושע בן לוי. Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi. So רבי שמעון
בר עקבא Rabbi Shimon bar Ukva was in front of רבי שמעון
בן פזי. Rabbi Shimon ben Pazi. אמר ליה, amar lei, so he
says to רבי שמעון בן פזי, Rabbi Shimon ben Pazi, "Rabbi אגדתא,
Agadta, מאי דכתיב? mai d'chsiv? What's meant by the פסוק pasuk ברכי
נפשי את ה'
וכל..." Barchi nafshi es Hashem v'chol... מדת בשר ודם, midat basar vadam,
the way of flesh
and blood, צר צורה גבי הכותל, tzar tzura gabei hakotel, so he
draws a shape on the wall, ואינו יכול
להטיל בו רוח ונשמה קרביים ובני
מעיים, ve'eino yachol lehatil bo ruach veneshama keravim uvenei me'ayim, cannot fill
it with spirit, with a soul, innards, with, you know, inner internal
organs. You know, we can draw things, we can't create life. והקדוש
ברוך הוא אינו כן, ve'hakadosh baruch hu eino ken, God is not
this way. צר צורה בתוך צורה, tzar tzura betoch tzura, He makes
an image inside of an image, presumably he means like our inner
organs, ומטיל בה רוח ונשמה קרביים ובני מעיים, umetil bah ruach veneshama
keravim uvenei me'ayim,
and he puts inside of us spirit and soul, inner internal organs
and intestines. והיינו דאמרה חנה, ve'hainu de'amrah Chanah, that's what Chanah said:
אין קדוש כה' כי אין בלתך, ein kadosh kaShem ki ein biltecha,
there's no one holy as God, there's none like You. ואין צור
כאלהינו, ve'ein tzur kelokeinu, there is no rock like our God. מאי
ואין צור כאלהינו? mai ve'ein tzur kelokeinu? What does it mean there's
no rock like our God? אין צייר כאלהינו. ein tzaiyar kelokeinu. There
is no one that can be a fashioner like our God, that
can fashion something and instill it with life. So apparently he understood
so... מאי כי אין בלתך? mai ki ein biltecha?
Well, let's first see the add-on. What's meant that there is none
like You, none other than You? אמר רב יהודה בר מנסיא, Amar
Rav Yehuda bar Menasya, אל תקרי כי אין בלתך, al tikri ki
ein biltecha, there is none other than You, אלא אין לבלותך, ela
ein livalotecha, there's no way to wear You out, wear You away.
שלא כמדת הקדוש ברוך הוא מדת בשר ודם, shelo k'midat hakadosh baruch
hu midat basar vadam, again, the way of God is not the
way of flesh and blood. מדת בשר ודם מעשה ידיו מבלין אותו,
midat basar vadam ma'aseh yadav mavlin oto, the way of flesh and
blood is the things that we create outlive us. Right? As you
all know, not only that, you go to the Metropolitan Museum, you
know, you see all of the statues, whatever, you know, they far
outlive the people that created them. והקדוש ברוך הוא מבלה מעשיו. ve'hakadosh
baruch hu mevaleh ma'asav. God outlives God's creatures. God creates people, they
finally, even though it's the same, I think, the image of fashioning
objects, God fashions us, but in the end, ultimately, God, you know,
God outlives us.
Okay, so that was his answer. Funny exactly, you know, what he...
first of all, the ואין צור, ve'ein tzur, what's the problem with
the פסוק Pasuk ואין צור כאלהינו? ve'ein tzur kelokeinu? Just interpret it
normally. But again, the מהרש"א Maharsha says normally, yes, we have צור
tzur mentioned by God, הצור תמים פעלו, HaTzur tamim po'alo, the צור.
tzur. But ואין צור כאלהינו ve'ein tzur kelokeinu puts it on like
a list, on like a comparison. There's no צור tzur as much
as God. But there are other rocks out there. So rock, you
know, God who's the rock, you know, that's the sense, like the
only. When you say there's none like God, except, okay, but there
are others that are maybe not as good as God, but they're
on the same sort of range of comparison. So therefore it interprets
it, no, no, no, we're talking about not צור tzur like the
rock, but צייר, tzaiyar, the fashioner. It is also, I would say,
interesting given the context of the Roman world that they gave the
example of drawing an image on a wall. You would have thought
they would have given the image of making a statue, which is
an attempt to be more lifelike. And even if you make a
statue, you don't make it with inner organs, you don't make it
with the soul. You know, it's not exactly clear to me the
idea of why they went to the sort of drawing the image
on the wall. But anyway.
Yeah, because, you know, I'm thinking about like Egypt, you
know,
and הלא צורה זה אחרת, halo tzura zeh acheret,
you know, the עגל, Eigel, you know, and במצרים, be'Mitzrayim, it's mentioned
in a, in במצרים be'Mitzrayim kind of thing. But הציור hatziyur is
a צייר.
tzaiyar. Well, that's true. צייר tzaiyar is more two-dimensional. So if the
דרשה drasha is on צייר, tzaiyar, then you might be right, then
that is more two-dimensional.
Anyway, that seems to be the דרשה drasha of כל קרבי, kol
keravai, my innards, like that human beings can draw like outer images,
but they can't draw three-dimensional... make three-dimensional... but they can't make, you
know, organs and the inside and so on. I mean, even nowadays,
we clone or whatever, it's with the raw materials, you know, it's
really just sort of tapping into that potential within the creation that
asks for through replication, replicating itself. We actually don't create that. What's
that poem about... no,
was that what... No, the one about, I don't know what you're
talking about, I was talking about the more, what was it, Ozymandias
or something, something like only God can... make a tree? How does
that go? Anyway, what, what that פסוק, pasuk, it's not a פסוק.
pasuk. Okay. What were you talking about? What, what poem were you
talking about? Ozymandias.
Right, king of kings. Right, right, right. Look upon my works, ye
mighty, and despair. Nothing remains beside... round the decay of that colossal
wreck, boundless and bare, the lone
and level sands stretch far away. Oh, I see. Oh, I see.
It's about the futility of
human humanity, very nice. Okay. Alright, anyway, now the גמרא Gemara continues.
Okay, so that's what he did with that דרשה. drasha. Pretty much
a straight explication of ברכי נפשי, Barchi Nafshi, you know, כל קרבי,
kol keravai, you know, about the wonder of God. So now the
גמרא Gemara says he wasn't interested in that answer. He says back
to him, אמר ליה אנה הכי קאמינא לך. Amar lei ana hachi
ka'amina lach. I wasn't interested in you just sort of giving a
דרש דרשה drash drasha on כל קרבי, kol keravai, which is more
or less פשט pshat of the פסוקים, Psukim, just elaborating on it.
But here's my question. הני חמשה ברכי נפשי כנגד מי אמרן דוד?
Hani chamisha Barchi Nafshi keneged mi amran David? Why did he say
ברכי נפשי Barchi Nafshi five times, ברכי נפשי, Barchi Nafshi, like the
דרשה drasha we did
before, לא אמרן אלא כנגד הקדוש ברוך הוא, lo amran ela keneged
hakadosh baruch hu, God, וכנגד נשמה. vekeneged neshama. And the soul because
it's ברכי נפשי את ה׳, Barchi nafshi et Hashem, ברכי נפשי את
ה׳, Barchi nafshi et Hashem, my soul God, my soul God. So
why five times? מה הקדוש ברוך הוא מלא כל העולם Ma hakadosh
baruch hu malei kol haolam because there are five ways in which
the soul is similar to God, as it's like an as it's
like a חלק אלוה ממעל, chelek eloka mima'al, is like a part
is like a is like some some you know essence of God.
The same way God fills the entire world, אף נשמה מלאה כל
הגוף. af neshama malei kol haguf.
The soul fills the entire body. מה הקדוש ברוך הוא רואה ואינו
נראה, Ma hakadosh baruch hu ro'eh ve'eino nir'eh, the same way God
sees but cannot be seen, אף נשמה רואה ואינה נראית. af neshama
ro'ah ve'eino nir'et. The soul can see, right? Understand the soul as
our you know that which is the person inside of our physical
being. So we see but you cannot see the soul. מה הקדוש
ברוך הוא זן את כל העולם כולו, Ma hakadosh baruch hu zan
et kol haolam kulo, the same way God sustains the entire world,
אף נשמה זנה את כל הגוף. af neshama zana et kol haguf.
So similarly the the soul you know sort of sustains the entire
body. Presumably meaning that you know if you were to put food
in a body once it's dead, it wouldn't cause it to to
you know it wouldn't provide sustenance. There's some, again, it's the sort
of the human life within us that processes the food and you
know and causes all parts of the body to be sustained through
what we eat. מה הקדוש ברוך הוא טהור, Ma hakadosh baruch hu
tahor, the same way God is טהור, tahor, אף נשמה טהורה, af
neshama tehorah, the soul is טהורה, tehorah, right? אלקי נשמה שנתת בי
טהורה היא Elokai neshama shenatata bi tehorah hi and you might remember
at the end of נדה Niddah we actually learned something that very
much made the comparison between the טהור tahor soul that we have
been given by the טהור tahor God, pure. מה הקדוש ברוך הוא
יושב בחדרי חדרים, Ma hakadosh baruch hu yoshev bechadrei chadarim, the same
way God lives in the innermost chamber, interesting, אף נשמה יושבת בחדרי
חדרים. af neshama yoshevet bechadrei chadarim.
The soul lives in the innermost chamber. Not exactly sure what that
means. I mean the soul a minute ago we said that God
fills the world and the soul fills the body and it can't
it's not visible. So what exactly it means that it's in the
innermost chamber?
It's within us, it's not like you know what's something
you see, I think it's sort of I know but it already
said it fills our body and it can't be seen so what's
more being added like the innermost chamber? That sounds like it's more
in a compartmentalized you know not so much totally suffusing. Not exactly
sure what to make of that. I understand but I'm interested if
people have any insight on that. Anyway, יבוא מי שיש בו חמשה
דברים הללו וישבח למי שיש בו חמשה דברים הללו. Yavo mi sheyesh
bo chamisha devarim elalu veyishabe'ach lemi sheyesh bo chamisha devarim elalu. Let
the one that has these five qualities, the soul that is similar
to God in these ways, is an essence of God, let the
soul come and praise God who has these five qualities. So again
with the חדרי חדרים chadrei chadarim thing aside and I'm open for
any interpretations but obviously on the one hand the power of this
statement is is that you know the sense of and I think
it's also very interesting having just compared it to you know אין
צור כאלקינו Ein tzur kelokeinu which is the other which is the
other דרשה drasha which is sort of you know this idea of
of being created בצלם אלקים betzelem Elokim in the image of God.
So of course that can be very treated very literally you know
and leads to anthropomorphizing anthropomorphisms literally and that the human form is
somehow similar to the divine form, okay? And the first דרשה drasha
you know was about God's ability it was partly about the soul
but partly about the wonder of the human body you know the
organs and life and so on. And this דרשה drasha very much
focuses on that that aspect in which we are like God has
to do with the soul, not the body and emphasize the way
in which the soul is a portion of God. So on the
one hand it's a very beautiful דרשה drasha in sort of in
in really trying to drive home that sense that the you know
the divine within all of us and our soul is divine but
on the other hand I have to tell you that it's fascinating
to me some of these ideas of God filling the world and
God being זן את כל העולם zan et kol haolam because if
you think about that by the analogy to the soul it's much
less the transcendent idea of God that we normally have, right? That
God somehow is above the world and we say God sustains the
world and it's like you know God somehow you know provides food
on this world and creates a physical world in which we have
our sustenance and we raise crops and animals find their food but
if you make the comparison to the soul it's much greater sense
of God's of God's immanence. Like God infuses the world and God's
infusing of the world is what provides for the sustenance of the
world. So it's a much more sort of immanent rather than transcendent
aspect of God so I think it's fascinating to think about what
the metaphor does in the reverse as well. Okay so that's what
he wanted to get out of that
פסוק. pasuk. Alright moving on, אמר רב המנונא מאי דכתיב? Amar Rav
Hamnuna mai dechtiv? What is meant by the פסוק pasuk מי כחכם
ומי יודע פשר דבר? mi kechecham u'mi yode'a pesher davar? Who is
the wise person and who knows the explanation of the matter? Now
this does isn't a continuation of the previous דרשה, drasha, this is
finally gonna get us sort of move us back to the discussion
of halakhic issues and about סמיכת גאולה לתפילה semichas geulah l'tefillah which
you might remember we discussed a little while ago. Anyway who is
the wise person and who knows the meaning of the matter? מי
כהקדוש ברוך הוא שיודע לעשות פשרה בין שני צדיקים? Mi k'hakadosh baruch
hu sheyode'a la'asos peshara bein shenei tzaddikim? Who is like God that
knows how to make a compromise between two righteous people? בין חזקיהו
לישעיהו, bein Chizkiyahu l'Yeshayahu, between חזקיהו Chizkiyahu the king and ישעיהו Yeshayahu
the prophet. חזקיהו אמר, Chizkiyahu amar, חזקיהו Chizkiyahu when he got sick,
if you know the story you know חזקיהו Chizkiyahu got sick and
was about to die and then ישעיהו Yeshayahu came to visit him.
So חזקיהו אמר Chizkiyahu amar ליתי ישעיהו גבאי. leiyisei Yeshayahu gabai. You
know what? If ישעיהו Yeshayahu has something he wants to say, let
him come
in, let him come to me. come say it to me. ישעיהו
אמר, Yeshayahu amar, ישעיהו Yeshayahu said, ליתי חזקיהו גבאי, leisi Chizkiyahu gabai,
if חזקיהו Chizkiyahu wants to hear what God says, let חזקיהו Chizkiyahu
come to me. דהכי אשכחן ביהורם בן אחאב, dehachi ashchichan bi-Yehoram ben
Achav, here we found by יהורם Yehoram the son of אחאב, Achav,
דאזל לגבי אלישע, de'azal legabei Elisha, he went to אלישע, Elisha, אליהו's
Eliyahu replacement. So anyway each one of them was standing on their
honor, refusing to go visit the other one, you know, saying if
he has something to say, let him come to me. מהרש"א Maharsha
points out, by the way, that this is not, that this is
very much based in the פסוקים, pesukim, because in the פסוקים, pesukim,
when חזקיהו Chizkiyahu and ישעיהו Yeshayahu talk, they do it through messengers.
The פסוקים pesukim are always saying that חזקיהו Chizkiyahu sent to ישעיהו,
Yeshayahu, ישעיהו Yeshayahu sent to חזקיהו. Chizkiyahu. So it seems pretty clear
that no one was willing to go to the other person, like
they all had to communicate through somebody else. They were all standing
on their honor.
What?
Proved that somebody because אחאב Achav actually went out to see אליהו.
Eliyahu.
That's true. Right, that is true. When things got bad, אחאב Achav
went to seek אליהו. Eliyahu. Well things are about to get bad
here, but yeah, that is true. Anyway, so each one was standing
on his honor. And God wanted them to get together for what
purpose, not just make שלום, shalom, but there was a larger purpose
here. Let's take a look. מה עשה הקדוש ברוך הוא, Ma asa
HaKadosh Baruch Hu, what did God do? הביא יסורין על חזקיהו, Heivi
yisurin al Chizkiyahu, he brought afflictions, maybe echoing back to the יסורין
yisurin we saw before, afflictions on חזקיהו. Chizkiyahu. ואמר לו לישעיהו Ve-amar
lo li-Yeshayahu and he said to ישעיהו, Yeshayahu, לך בקר את החולה,
leich bakaid et ha-choleh, go visit the him, he's sick. Meaning don't
visit him because you have a prophecy to give him, then you'll
feel he should be coming to you if he wants a prophecy.
Go visit him as a basic act of human kindness. He's sick,
you visit a sick person.
שנאמר בימים ההם חלה חזקיהו למות, Shenemar ba-yamim ha-heim chalah Chizkiyahu la-mut,
חזקיהו Chizkiyahu was ill, he was going to die. ויבא אליו ישעיהו
בן אמוץ הנביא, Va-yavo eilav Yeshayahu ben Amotz ha-navi, and ישעיהו Yeshayahu
son of אמוץ Amotz the prophet came to him. ויאמר אליו Va-yomer
eilav and he said to him, כה אמר ה' צו לביתך כי
מת אתה ולא תחיה. Koh amar Hashem tzav le-veisecha ki meis atah
ve-lo sichyeh. Give command to your house, sort of get your affairs
in order, you are going to die and you will not live.
So actually and this ultimately was not just visiting him, but there
was a message here and this presumably was also the prophecy that
he needed to give him. Although the גמרא Gemara is going to
ask that, very good, the גמרא Gemara will ask that. מאי, Mai,
see that, כי מת אתה ולא תחיה? ki meis atah ve-lo sichyeh?
What does it mean you will die and not live? Why does
it have to say it twice? מת אתה בעולם הזה, Meis atah
ba-olam ha-zeh, you'll die in this world, ולא תחיה לעולם הבא, ve-lo
sichyeh la-olam ha-ba, and you won't even get עולם הבא. Olam HaBa.
Now this is חזקיהו Chizkiyahu who was basically one of the few
righteous kings that they had in hundreds of years. So what does
this mean לא תחיה לעולם הבא? lo sichyeh la-olam ha-ba? אמר ליה,
Amar lei, so חזקיהו Chizkiyahu said to him, מאי כולי האי, mai
kulei hai, what's all this about? אמר ליה, Amar lei, he said
to him, משום דלא עסקת בפריה ורביה, mishum de-lo asakta be-piryah ve-rivyah,
because you have not involved yourself in procreating. אמר ליה, Amar lei,
because we know that מנשה Menashe who is the son of חזקיהו
Chizkiyahu was a very wicked king. He was 12 years old when
חזקיהו Chizkiyahu died. And actually the end of this story is that
חזקיהו Chizkiyahu prays to God and is given 15 more years to
live. So it's clear that his son and presumably his only son,
because he was the son that was going to inherit him, was
born after this event and because he was only 12 years old
when he died 15 years later. So therefore you have not been
involved in פרו ורבו, pru u-revu, you've not done this very important
מצוה. mitzvah. אמר ליה, Amar lei, so he said, חזקיהו Chizkiyahu said
back to ישעיהו, Yeshayahu, here's why I didn't do it. משום דחזאי
לי ברוח הקודש, mishum de-chazai li be-ruach ha-kodesh, because
I see with the divine spirit, דנפקי מינאי בנין דלא מעלו, de-nafki
minai banin de-lo ma'alu, that I will have children that are not
good children, דלא מעלו, de-lo ma'alu, you know, that they're not worthy
children, that they'll be sinners. אמר ליה, Amar lei, so he said
back to him, famous line here, I mean famous in that it's
quoted elsewhere, not that the גמרא Gemara has it, but this is
one place it says it. בהדי כבשי דרחמנא למה לך? Be-hadai kavshi
de-Rachmana lamah lach? These hidden things of God, what interest are they
of yours? Don't you worry about God's חשבונות. cheshbonos. מאי דמפקדת איבעיא
לך למעבד, Mai de-mifkadat ibaya lach le-me'evad,
what you're commanded you have to do, you do your obligation. ומאי
דניחא קמי קודשא בריך הוא לעבד לעבד, U-mai de-nicha kamey Kudsha Brich
Hu le-eved le-eved,
what God wants God will do, that's not your responsibility. You do
your מצוות, mitzvos, you let God worry about God's issues. You should
still be doing the מצוות, mitzvos, you should be having kids. Don't
worry about what you foresee in רוח הקודש. ruach ha-kodesh. Also obviously
raises questions about בחירה חפשית bechirah chafshis and so on. Okay, but
that was the response. אמר ליה, Amar lei, so he said, so
this is a good response, חזקיהו Chizkiyahu said back to ישעיהו, Yeshayahu,
השתא הב לי ברתך, hashta hav li bartach, okay,
so give me your daughter as a wife. אפשר דגרמה זכותך דידי
ודידך ונפקי מינאי בנין דמעלו, Efshar de-garma zechusach didi ve-didach ve-nafki minai
banin de-ma'alu,
maybe both your merit, mine and yours, will combine that the children
will be good kids, will be righteous children and not wicked children.
So basically he was calling him on it. If you say I
should have faith, just do what I'm supposed to, not worry about
what I see in the future, fine, let's see if you'll put
your money where your mouth is. Let me marry your daughter. אמר
ליה, Amar lei, so ישעיהו Yeshayahu said back to him, כבר נגזר
עליך גזירה, kevar nigzar alecha gezeirah,
the edict has already been decreed. What does that mean the edict
has already been decreed? It means you're going to have wicked kids?
No, no, so it doesn't mean you're going to have wicked kids.
It could mean that, because the later גמרא Gemara doesn't sound that
way, and anyway that would really make it tough if it since
was like there was no
hope. So and
what?
So he's saying, you know, we're not going to have, can't have
kids. Yeah. Well, a, it's not going to help you not die,
but b, if you even if you wanted to do it now,
he was first saying it's too late because you're about to die.
So you don't have time to have children. Right? So אמר ליה,
Amar lei, so he said to him, בן אמוץ, Ben Amotz, he
said to him, notice now the language switches to the much more
to the less, he's no longer talking ישעיהו הנביא, Yeshayahu Hanavi, whatever,
בן אמוץ, Ben Amotz, it's like a more familiar even derogatory way
of referring. Like when the גמרא Gemara sometimes has בני ישראל Bnei
Yisrael complaining about משה, Moshe, they call him בן עמרם. Ben Amram.
What does this בן עמרם Ben Amram think about us, whatever, bringing
him cutting him down to size. בן אמוץ, Ben Amotz, son of
Amotz, כלה נבואתך וצא, Kalei nevuatcha vetezei,
end your prophecy and get out of here. כך מקובלני, Kach mekublani,
I don't buy what you're saying. כך מקובלני מבית אבי אבא, Kach
mekublani beveit avi aba, this is the tradition I have from my
grandfather's house, meaning דוד, David, אפילו חרב חדה מונחת על צוארו של
אדם אל ימנע עצמו מן הרחמים, Afilu cherev hada munachat al tzavaro
shel adam al yimna atzmo min harachamim, even a sharp sword is
at a person's
neck, you should not hold yourself back from divine compassion, from prayer.
God can always reverse the edict.
If you take a look רש״י Rashi says, אבי אבא, Avi aba,
three lines from the bottom, דוד David שראה המלאך וחרבו שלופה בידו
she-ra'at hamal'ach vecharbo shelufa beyado בסוף ספר שמואל, besof sefer Shmuel,
he saw the angel with a sword against the sword, ולא מנע
עצמו מן הרחמים, velo mana etzmo min harachamim, he prayed to God
and it was he did not die. So he says, I don't
buy that I cannot reverse this. איתמר נמי, Itmar nami, רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan ורבי אלעזר ve-Rabbi Elazar דאמרי תרווייהו, de-amrei tarvaihu, they both
said, אפילו חרב חדה מונחת על צוארו של אדם אל ימנע עצמו
מן הרחמים afilu cherev hada munachat al tzavaro shel adam al yimna
atzmo min harachamim שנאמר, shene'emar, הן יקטלני לו איחל, hen yiktleni lo
ayachel, even if God will kill me, I will still seek out
God.
Now we're not done with the story. Let's turn let's turn the
עמוד amud back. What? We're not done with the story. You'll tell
me what you don't understand after the story's over. אמר רבי חנן,
Amar Rabbi Chanan, said רבי חנן, Rabbi Chanan, אפילו בעל החלומות אומר
לו לאדם למחר הוא מת, afilu ba'al hachalomot omer lo leadam lemachar
hu met, even if the owner of the dreams, like somehow a
vision in your dream comes to you and says to you you
will die tomorrow, אל ימנע עצמו מן הרחמים, al yimna atzmo min
harachamim, there's always a chance you should not hold yourself back from
divine compassion, שנאמר כי ברוב חלומות והבלים ודברים הרבה כי את האלוהים
ירא, shene'emar ki berov chalomot ve-havalim udevarim harbeh ki et ha'elohim yere,
because all of these dreams and the nonsense, there's always a certain
amount of falseness in dreams, but you should fear God ultimately, fear
God that can always change things. מיד, Miyad, so חזקיהו Chizkiyahu said
no, I believe that there still is hope, ויסב חזקיהו פניו אל
הקיר ויתפלל אל ה׳, vayasev Chizkiyahu panav el hakir vayitpalel el Hashem,
he turned to the wall and he prayed to God. And the
end of the story is that God said he gave him fifteen
more years of life, that he was right to have that hope
and that faith in God. It is interesting by the way, again
because this idea that he says things can still be reversed, he
also had this little hope that he was going to reverse the
issue about how the kids would turn out. And although Michael pointed
out, the מהרש״א Maharsha says it's clear when ישעיהו Yeshayahu says no,
נגזרה גזירה, nigzera gzeira,
it sounds like he means like you're not going to live, not
like your kid is definitely going to be wicked, but it's possible
that was part of the subtext as well. ישעיהו Yeshayahu just thinks
he's the נביא, Navi, this is what God says, this is the
way things are, they're not going to change. Okay? So he says
and חזקיהו Chizkiyahu had hope both that maybe he could do something
his kid would be better and maybe he could pray and he
could live. So it turns out he did live, but I mean
his kid was מנשה, Menashe, which raises questions about and in the
end you're sort of left wondering like if ישעיהו Yeshayahu had agreed
and
ישעיהו Yeshayahu had given over his daughter in marriage to חזקיהו, Chizkiyahu,
maybe things who knows could have changed. What?
No, רוח הקודש
ruach
hakodesh
vision because he's saying that I see that you're going to have
bad children. But he's saying no נגזרה גזירה. nigzera gzeira. So he's
saying no, no, I'm the נביא, Navi, I know the רוח הקודש,
ruach hakodesh, you can't have a רוח הקודש ruach hakodesh vision.
Right, yeah, yeah, ישעיהו Yeshayahu is just saying this is the way
it is, things aren't going to change, and חזקיהו Chizkiyahu has hope
that maybe we can do things and things will change. So initially
he didn't want to have kids, right? He was not such a
determinist, he wanted to be in control of the way things were
going to work out and if his kids weren't going to be
good he didn't want to have them. But at least anyway at
this moment he thinks he can change things, he can get God
to let him live, he can get good kids, and ישעיהו Yeshayahu
is not moving. And in the end the kid turns out bad
but maybe who knows what would have happened if ישעיהו Yeshayahu would
have agreed to this plan.
בהדי כבשי דרחמנא למה לך.
Bahadei
kavshei deRachmana lama lach.
Yeah, right, I mean he's
right, you lived but in
the end God got his way in the long run.
Well, right, that is true too. You mean that in the end
we can only do so much and
your rebelling actually enabled that because you said you'd have no children,
right, okay.
So your desire to live ultimately brought about the divine plan regardless,
sort of like the reverse of what the גמרא Gemara sometimes like
the famous גמרא Gemara
about how דוד David was born or יהודה Yehuda was born. Anyway,
ultimately it did work out but he still okay so what
he's telling him anyway
okay hold on I'll get back to that let's finish the story
we'll talk a little bit more about that. So אמר רבי שמעון
בן לקיש Amar Rebbi Shimon ben Lakish so what does it mean
I'm sorry ויסב חזקיהו פניו אל הקיר Vayeishev Chizkiyahu panav el hakir
he turned to the wall ויתפלל אל השם. vayitpallel el Hashem. מה
קיר? Ma kir? Why does it say he turned to the wall?
What's the significance of that? אמר רבי שמעון בן לקיש Amar Rebbi
Shimon ben Lakish מקירות לבו mikirot libo
from the walls of the chambers of his heart from the very
depths of his soul שנאמר מעי מעי אוחילה קירות לבי shenemar me'ai
me'ai ochila kirot libi my inwards will sort of yearn will like
reach out to God from the depths of my heart the walls
of my heart. לוי אמר Levi amar so it says how sort
of deep and sincere the prayer is. לוי אמר Levi amar על
עסקי הקיר al iskei hakir regarding the wall אמר לפניו רבונו של
עולם amar lefanav Ribono Shel Olam Master of the Universe מה שונמית
שלא עשתה אלא קיר אחת קטנה החיית בנה ma Shunammis shelo asta
ela kir achat ketana hechayita bna the Shunammite right in the story
of אלישע Elisha she made a little wall a little chamber a
room for אלישע Elisha to have a private room when he came
and when her son died her son was brought back to life.
אבי אבא Avi aba my grandfather דוד David or שלמה Shlomo שחיפה
היכל כולו בכסף וזהב shechippa heichal kulo bechessef vezahav
didn't just make one wall made the entire temple and plated it
with gold and silver על אחת כמה וכמה al achas kama vekama
how much more should I merit to live. זכור נא את אשר
התהלכתי לפניך Zechor na es asher hishallachti lefanecha
remember how I have walked before you
באמת ובלב שלם והטוב בעיניך עשיתי be'emes ubelev shalem uvatov be'einecha asiti
and I have done what is good in your eyes. This is
quoted from ספר ישעיהו Sefer Yeshayahu quoting from the prayer of חזקיהו.
Chizkiyahu. מאי והטוב בעיניך עשיתי? Mai uvatov be'einecha asiti? What does it
mean I've done what is good in your eyes? אמר יהודה אמר
רב שסמך גאולה לתפילה. Amar Yehuda amar Rav shesamach geula litefilla.
This is why we wanted it. This is the one thing he
is praying to God why he deserves to live because סמך גאולה
לתפילה samach geula litefilla because he said גאל ישראל Ga'al Yisrael right
before שמונה עשרה. Shmoneh Esrei. Now that's a pretty pretty big for
you know sort of reward for that. I'll get back to that
in a minute again let's read a little bit more and then
we'll take a step back. רבי לוי אמר שגנז ספר רפואות Rebbi
Levi amar sheganaz sefer refuos because he hid the book of healings.
So then we're going to go into that for a minute. So
let me first talk a little bit about the סמך גאולה לתפילה
samach geula litefilla which is
the מהרש"א Maharsha says a beautiful thing there. He says that the
סמך גאולה לתפילה samach geula litefilla is not just the what do
you call it is not just the the what we've been talking
about you say גאל ישראל Ga'al Yisrael at the end of שמע
Shema and then you say שמונה עשרה. Shmoneh Esrei. But he says
that actually was חזקיהו's Chizkiyahu life because first right before this story
about him dying and ישעיהו Yeshayahu visiting him or falling sick was
the story about how סנחריב Sancheriv was you know was destroyed the
armies of סנחריב Sancheriv was destroyed. So he says there was like
a סמך גאולה לתפילה samach geula litefilla that story of the גאולה
geula preceded the story of his praying to God in this story
of him growing sick. But one might want add to that the
idea that there's a famous I mean that sort of reminding me
of the famous מדרש Midrash that says that you know that the
משיח Mashiach would have been חזקיהו Chizkiyahu had he just said שירה
shira when this גאולה geula occurred at this moment of סנחריב. Sancheriv.
So in a way you know that sort of again sort of
it doesn't exactly work because he didn't do it but it sort
of speaks to the idea that when one experiences you know the
power of God and the salvation of God that that what that
that demands in terms of responding to it and the שירה shira
and the תפילה tefilla and the reacting to sort of that direct
experience of God's salvation and the connecting to God and how חזקיהו
Chizkiyahu could have been the משיח Mashiach for you know were it
not for that. So here too you know there's some sense of
the power I don't know maybe I'm going a little bit afield
here but the power of the תפילה tefilla when it comes to
his sense of you know sort of the reverse of גאולה לתפילה
geula litefilla is here the sense that his life is in abeyance
and it leads to prayer right and those are really like the
two types of experiences of prayer. One is a sort of ממעמקים
mimamakim experience that you know that things are what's the fear and
what's you know and sort of and the prayer out of out
of out of anguish and out of a sense of what might
be coming and then there's the prayer out of joy and a
sort of more of the שבח shevach and the הלל hallel and
so on. So you have sort of in a way you have
an interesting thing again I'm not sure exactly this exactly fitting in
that he was סמך גאולה לתפילה samach geula litefilla but he wasn't
able to respond to the גאולה geula with a תפילה tefilla and
what he did respond to the תפילה tefilla was the מת אתה
ולא תחיה mesa ata velo tichye and sadly that very often is
our experience. When good things happen you know we take it for
granted or whatever we don't really almost see God's hand in them
and when it's a bad things then we all turn to God
for salvation but when the actual salvation happens how often does it
lead to the שבח? shevach? So anyway interestingly here the גמרא Gemara
saying that
that סמך גאולה לתפילה samach geula litefilla is so important that maybe
that's what merits here now this תפילה tefilla to be answered. If
you're able to when the salvation occurs to respond to it with
תפילה tefilla you know then then that also merits you at this
moment to be have that prayer answered. Yes.
When the נביא navi said to
חזקיה Chizkiya מת ולא תחיה. mes velo tichye. Did he understand that
that meant that he lost his עולם הבא? olam haba?
Oh, I have no idea.
Because if he did and was given extra years you would think
that he would be עוסק osek in פריה ורביה periyah u'reviyah to
save his עולם הבא. olam haba. Right.
Well, he was עוסק osek in פריה ורביה. periyah u'reviyah. That's when
he had מנשה. Menashe.
So maybe he did save it?
I know. Yeah, I don't think we're supposed to assume at the
end of the story when he's answered that he's still has lost
his עולם הבא. olam haba. When God gives him back 15 years,
I think we're supposed to assume that he's also getting his עולם
הבא olam haba back, especially because if he's עוסק osek in פריה
ורביה. periyah u'reviyah. But as דב Dov points out, in the end
God wins because God's מנשה Menashe gets born. So, yes.
And מנשה Menashe is not all bad, the rabbis struggled with...
Yeah, מנשה Menashe also does תשובה. teshuvah. That's also true. מנשה Menashe
is also a fascinating story of having done תשובה. teshuvah. Right.
He would not have been conceived if ישעיהו Yeshayahu had more faith.
Right. Right, that's an interesting,
yeah.
That's an interesting, yeah.
It's interesting because one story is about how you cannot get in
the way of God's plan and another story is you can always
ask God to change his plan. Right.
Right. That's what I was focusing on that he was trying to
change, ישעיהו Yeshayahu was saying you can't change and then דב Dov
said yeah great, he tried to change God's plan and then in
the end God's ultimate plan, if that was God's plan, מנשה Menashe
was born, at least that prophecy in the end came through.
The חז"ל Chazal say you even have a knife in, you have
a sword
at your throat, right,
and you can still pray. That's changing God's...
Absolutely, right. So, right, right, I agree. I think that that's exactly
the tension going on here.
Was God's plan to get you...
exactly, exactly, exactly. So anyway, one other point or two other points
about the בהדי כבשי דרחמנא למה לך. bahadei kavshei d'rachmana lamma lach.
You know, that's a powerful statement which is don't worry about God,
you just do your responsibility. Because that sometimes is used, you know,
well I'll give you an example how is that used. On the
one hand, there's a, you know, the Rav Waldenberg, the ציץ אליעזר,
Tzitz Eliezer, is quite lenient when it comes to issues relating to
abortion, especially if it has to do with questions about the health
of the parent, of the mother, or sometimes even about the child
is going to be born with like a serious genetic disease, like
Tay-Sachs and so on. So that's on the one hand. But that's
when the child already has that genetic disease. But then somebody asks
a question like can you use birth control if you find out,
you know, never have any kids if the parents find out that
they're carriers. You know, there's a likelihood that the kid will have
this disease. So on the one hand he says, well maybe yes,
because you know פרו ורבו, peru u'revu, here's exactly this issue of
פרו ורבו, peru u'revu, although it's a big מצוה, mitzvah, but you
know you don't do מצוות, mitzvot, you know, you can passively refrain
from positive מצוות mitzvot sometimes if there's a tremendous negative consequence. You
know, even sometimes it just costs a lot of money, certainly something
like this, which at the emotional cost and so on. But then
he says, but maybe we should say like בהדי כבשי דרחמנא למה
לך. bahadei kavshei d'rachmana lamma lach. You know, look, you know, what
is it us to sort of play God? You know, God will
figure out whether the kid has it or not. That's not definitely
going to happen anyway, it's usually like one in four or whatever,
you know, and therefore maybe we shouldn't be in a position to
make these types of חשבונות. cheshbonot. Now, there it's a little different,
there you actually know the genetics. It's not like רשע rasha or
צדיק tzaddik which in the end is about בחירה חופשית. bechirah chofshit.
In the end, he basically allows the use of birth control if
you know that the... if you find out you're going to be
carriers. But the very fact that he raises that question, you know,
on the one hand there's a powerful sort of theological statement, right,
which is so many people go around thinking they know exactly how
God runs the world and the right way they think God runs
the world, you know, that sort of allows them to decide how
they should act and how other people should act and so on.
You know, so in that way it's very powerful, you know, don't
worry about how God runs the world, you just have to do,
you know, your מצוות, mitzvot, you know, and so on. On the
other hand, you know, bringing it up in that context is a
little scary because, you know, we actually do know the likelihood and
how much should that, you know, we should be entitled to factor
that in to הלכה halakhah decision making, which is very much about
practical issues not about theological ones. Yes.
What's interesting is, you know, if he really had believed it from
the beginning, בהדי כבשי דרחמנא למה לך, bahadei kavshei d'rachmana lamma lach,
then he would have just from the beginning been עוסק osek פרו
ורבו peru u'revu no matter what, that he was going to have
a wicked son. He could have said, alright, I'm going to pray
that, you know, that he does תשובה. teshuvah.
That wasn't בהדי כבשי דרחמנא, bahadei kavshei d'rachmana, he had no idea
that that... that wasn't about his life being at risk.
It was קל וחומר kal v'chomer then.
Maybe. All right, let's keep on going. So now the גמרא Gemara
says like this. Okay, so then the other answer was that he
was גנז ספר רפואות. ganaz sefer refuot. Now what's that about? Well
let's read a little bit and we'll say something. תנו רבנן, Tanu
rabbanan, we taught. ששה דברים עשה חזקיה המלך, shisha devarim asah Chizkiyahu
hamelech, על ג' הודו לו ועל ג' לא הודו לו. al gimmel
hodu lo v'al gimmel lo hodu lo. So this is an elaboration
of a משנה Mishnah in פסחים. Pesachim. חזקיה Chizkiyahu did six things,
three the sages agreed to him and three they didn't agree to
it. על ג' הודו לו, al gimmel hodu lo, three they agreed
him. גנז ספר רפואות, ganaz sefer refuot, he hid the book of
healing, I'll talk about that in a minute, והודו לו, v'hodu lo,
they agreed to it. כתת נחש הנחשת, kitat nehash hanechoshet, he ground
up the iron snake, the copper snake that משה Moshe had made
because on the one hand it was a memory of what משה
Moshe had done and it had, and so on, but on the
other hand people were using it as like a talisman and a
way of healing themselves and almost like, you know,
it was almost being treated as an idol. והודו לו, v'hodu lo,
they said good idea, of course get rid of it, it's leading
people astray. גירר עצמות אביו על מטה של חבלים, girer atzmot aviv
al mitah shel chavalim, his father who was a wicked king rather...
showing him honor at the burial, he's going to drag him on
this sort of on this sort of coffin or whatever this bed
of rope as a way of maybe showing the people, you know,
to not learn from his father although he was a king he
did not deserve respect because of the evil doing.
רש"י Rashi says it's a way of getting atonement for the father
by this type of treatment of the body. והודו לו, vehodu lo,
that's a good point, yes, that trumps the כיבוד אב ואם kibbud
av va’em is trumped by this larger issue. ועל ג' לא הודו
לו, ve-al gimmel lo hodu lo, three they did not agree with
him. סיתם מי גיחון, satam mei Gihon, he sealed up the waters
of גיחון. Gihon. This is based on פסוקים, pesukim, I should tell
you, outside of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, that when the troops were to come
of סנחריב, Sancheriv, they should not find water. ולא הודו לו, ve-lo
hodu lo, they did not, they said that was not the right
action to take. Maybe he should have had more faith in God,
maybe he stopped up other waters but not that water. קיצץ דלתות
היכל ושיגרם למלך אשור, Kitzetz daltot Heichal ve-shigram le-melech Ashur, he cut
the doors of the היכל Heichal and sent them to the king
of אשור, Ashur, right? These were obviously very precious doors. So and
he sort of did it as a bribe, ולא הודו לו, ve-lo
hodu lo, they were not happy with that. Don't go bribing the
king of אשור, Ashur, just have faith in God and certainly don't
go bribe him with the doors of the היכל. Heichal. עיבר ניסן
בניסן ולא הודו לו. Iber Nissan be-Nissan ve-lo hodu lo.
And he made an extra month, an extra in ניסן, Nissan, right?
You can make an extra אדר, Adar, but it's before ראש חודש
ניסן. Rosh Chodesh Nissan. אדר, Adar, excuse me, but it's in ראש
חודש ניסן, Rosh Chodesh Nissan, it's before ראש חודש ניסן. Rosh Chodesh
Nissan. He did it once it was already ראש חודש ניסן. Rosh
Chodesh Nissan. Also actually based on פסוקים, pesukim, רש"י Rashi quotes them,
ולא הודו לו, ve-lo hodu lo, they didn't do it. מה חזא
חזקיהו? Mah chaza Chizkiyahu? ומאי חזא חזקיהו? u-mai chaza Chizkiyahu? ומאי חזא
חזקיהו? u-mai chaza Chizkiyahu? החודש הזה לכם ראש חדשים. ha-chodesh ha-zeh lachem
rosh chodashim.
How could he have thought to do that? We have a דרשה
drasha that says this is the month ahead of the month, talking
about ניסן. Nissan. זה ניסן ואין אחר ניסן. Zeh Nissan ve-ein acher
Nissan. Only this is ניסן. Nissan. You can't make another month into
ניסן, Nissan, so you can't make a second ניסן. Nissan. You could
make a second אדר, Adar, but you can't make a second ניסן.
Nissan. You can't have two ניסןs. Nissan This is the one head
month. אלא טעה בשמואל. Ella ta-ah bi-Shmuel. His error was about שמואל's
Shmuel teaching. דאמר שמואל, d'amar Shmuel, a little anachronistic, אין מעברים את
השנה ביום שלושים של אדר הואיל וראוי לקובעו ניסן. ein me-abrin et
ha-shanah be-yom shloshim shel Adar ho-il ve-ra-uy le-kov-o Nissan. You cannot make
an extra אדר Adar on day thirty of אדר Adar because day
thirty of אדר Adar could be ראש חודש ניסן. Rosh Chodesh Nissan.
Once it's in the potential ראש חודש ניסן, Rosh Chodesh Nissan, you
can no longer make an extra month. סבר הואיל וראוי לאו כמי
שהוקבע דמי. Savar ho-il ve-ra-uy lav ke-mi she-hukba dami. But so what,
it's still not ראש חודש ניסן, Rosh Chodesh Nissan, so he figured
he could still do it. And that was his mistake. So again,
a very interesting mix of sort of a larger sort of religious,
you know, political types of statements and then this sort of more
technical halachic issue. Now I do want to say something about
גנז ספר רפואות. ganaz sefer refuot. What does that mean? So the
traditional explanation is that this was a book of a lot of
medical cures, and similar to the נחש נחושת, nachash nechoshet, he was
bothered that people weren't praying to God. People would just check up
the sort of cures in the book, and they would get themselves
healed, and that was a problem because it was taking them away
from God. Now first of all there's a little bit of taking
yourself away from God because they thought of this magical powers of
the copper snake and actual practical medical advice, you know, from this
book. And is that really supposed to be? Like we're not supposed
to use good medical advice, we're just supposed to pray? I mean
the רמב"ן Ramban says, who himself was a doctor, that the purpose
of—and רש"י Rashi actually says it—the גמרא Gemara makes the דרשה drasha
of ורפא ירפא. verapo yerape. It says that you shall be healed
when somebody injures somebody that you shall heal him. The גמרא Gemara
says נתן רשות לרופא לרפאות. natan reshut le-rofe lerape-ot. From here we
see that doctors have a right to heal. So who needs to
give doctors a right to heal? Of course they have a right
to heal. So some say one explanation is that maybe they should
feel look, you know, I might wind up hurting the person, doing
more bad than good, maybe I shouldn't do anything. No, you have
to try to go ahead if you know what you're doing, you
have to try to heal. But the other explanation which both רש"י
Rashi and רמב"ן Ramban say is, maybe you'd say look, if God
made him sick, God will make him better, we should pray, we
shouldn't heal, right? Let God handle it. So no, you have a
responsibility actually the opposite of like כבשי דרחמנא. kivshei d'rachmana. Don't worry
about God, you do what you have to do, maybe the opposite,
you don't worry about God, you do what you have to do.
He's sick, it's your responsibility to heal. So you know given that,
it's a little funny like, oh, so we should hide the ספר
רפואות, sefer refuot, it makes getting better too easy, people don't pray
to God. So רמב"ם, Rambam, who of course was a doctor, very
much in his פירוש המשניות Peirush HaMishnayot is very angry at this
explanation. And he basically says, what type of nonsense is this that
you're not supposed to sort of use your medical knowledge to heal
people? I mean the very fact that you know you anyway when
we sort of see God and we say God is רופא חולים,
rofe cholim, it doesn't mean miraculous cures. It means that God has
given us the wisdom to develop the field of medicine and to
be able to help people, and that's God as רופא חולים rofe
cholim through human beings. So what's this nonsense that you're not supposed
to find out cures? So the רמב"ם Rambam says, tries to read
the ספר רפואות sefer refuot more like the whole story about the
נחש נחושת. nachash nechoshet. And he says that this was more like
astrological ways of healing or magical ways of healing and was misleading
people, and that's what it was about, it was not about real
ways of healing. Of course it is interesting that it's in this
story where he is sick and he turns to God and he
prays to God and God heals him. And when he's saying I
did the good thing, I hid the ספר רפואות. sefer refuot. So
it sort of does work with that other explanation which רמב"ם Rambam
doesn't like, like, look, hey God, you know, I got people to
turn to you when they were sick and not use the ספר
רפואות, sefer refuot, so I'm turning to you now and you—it does
sort of work very well with that version.
Okay, yes, let's just get everything down, the book of דברים. Devarim.
Yes. So then it was in...
No,
he wasn't in with it. No, that was יאשיהו. Yoshiyahu. יאשיהו, Yoshiyahu,
not Hezekiah. Right. Okay, let's, I know it's already 8:15, but we
started a little late. Let's just read a little bit further. אמר
רבי יוחנן משום רבי יוסי בן זמרא: Amar Rabbi Yochanan mishum Rabbi
Yosei ben Zimra: כל התולה בזכות עצמו, תולין לו בזכות אחר. Kol
hatoleh bizchut atzmo, tolin lo bizchut acher. Anybody who basically says, "do
it for me," in the end, if something is done for him,
it's done for in the sake of other people. וכל התולה בזכות
אחר, תולין לו בזכות עצמו. Vechol hatoleh bizchut acher, tolin lo bizchut
atzmo. If you say, "do it for somebody else," then it's done
for, it's attributed to him. What does this mean? משה תלה בזכות
אחר. Moshe talah bizchut acher. Moshe said, "do it for others," שנאמר:
shenemar: זכור לאברהם ליצחק
ולישראל עבדיך. Zechor le'Avraham le'Yitzchak u'le'Yisrael avadecha. God, please do it for
אברהם, Avraham, יצחק, Yitzchak, and יאקב, Yaakov, in terms of don't wipe
out the Jewish people. תלו לו בזכות עצמו. Talu lo bizchut atzmo.
In the end, it was said that God did it for him.
שנאמר: Shenemar: ויאמר להשמידם לולי משה בחירו עמד בפרץ. Vayomer lehashmidam lulei
Moshe bechiro amad baperetz. God would have wiped them out were
it not that משה, Moshe, his chosen, stood in the breach לפניו,
lefanav, להשיב חמתו מהשחית, lehashiv chamato mehashchit, to return back the anger
from destroy. חזקיהו תלה בזכות עצמו. Chizkiyahu talah bizchut atzmo.
Hezekiah said, "do it for me," or "I merit," דכתיב: dechtiv: זכר
נא את אשר התהלכתי לפניך. Zechor na et asher hithalachti lefanav.
Remember, God, how I have walked before You. תלו לו בזכות אחר.
Talu lo bizchut acher. So when in the end God did it,
He said He was doing it not for you, but for somebody
else. שנאמר: Shenemar: וגנותי אל העיר הזאת להושיעה למעני ולמען דוד עבדי.
Vegannoti el ha'ir hazot lehoshi'ah lema'ani u'lema'an David avdi. I have protected
over this city to save it, for My sake and for דוד
David My servant's sake. Not for you. והיינו דרבי יהושע בן לוי.
Vehaynu de'Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi.
That's what רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi says. דאמר
רבי יהושע בן לוי: De'amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi: מאי דכתיב: Mai
dechtiv: הנה לשלום מר לי מר? Hineh leshalom mar li mar? Behold
for peace, it is very bitter. אפילו בשעה ששיגר לו הקדוש ברוך
הוא שלום. Afilu besha'ah sheshigar lo HaKadosh Baruch Hu shalom. Even when
God sent him peace, מר הוא לו. mar hu lo. It was
a bitter pill because He was stating that He was doing it
for דוד David and not for him. Okay. We're going to, I'm
going to read a little bit further. I know people have to
go, they have to go, but we'll just try to get to
the משה. mishna. נעשה נא עלית קיר קטנה. Na'aseh na aliyat kir
ketanah. Let's make a little, because we mentioned that he was comparing
himself to the Shunammite who made the room for אלישע. Elisha. So
now we're going to have some דרשות drashot about the room for
אלישע. Elisha. Let's make for him a little קיר, kir, a little
wall. רב ושמואל. Rav u'Shmuel. חד אמר עליה פרועה היתה. Chad amar
aliyah peru'ah hayta. One said it was an exposed roof. There was
like an attic, but it hadn't, they hadn't put a roof on
it. וקירוה. Vekiruha. And they put a roof on it. So קיר
kir here meaning a roof, not a wall, a ceiling. Yeah. וחד
אמר אכסדרה גדולה היתה. Vechad amar achsadra gedolah hayta. No, it was
a big portico, like it was a big room. וחילקוה לשנים. Vechilkuha
leshnayim. And they literally put a wall to divide it into two
halves. בשלמא למאן דאמר אכסדרה היינו דכתיב קיר. Bishlama leman de'amar achsadra
haynu dechtiv kir.
If it's a big room, so it said a wall to divide
it into two rooms. אלא למאן דאמר עליה, Ela leman de'amar aliyah,
that it was a second story, מאי קיר? mai kir? What does
קיר kir mean? Like we said. שקירוה. Shekiruha. That like more like
not the, I think it might be even Aramaic, whatever, anyway not
that it means a roof, not a wall.
They roofed it. What's קטנה ketanah though?
They said, alright, I don't know. בשלמא למאן דאמר עליה היינו דכתיב
עליה. Bishlama leman de'amar aliyah haynu dechtiv aliyah. So if it was
the second story, that's why it says the second story. אלא למאן
דאמר אכסדרה, Ela leman de'amar achsadra, if it was a large room,
מאי עליה? mai aliyah? What does it mean a story? מעולה שבבתים.
Me'ulah shebebatim.
It means it was like a very beautiful, excellent house. A מעולה.
me'ulah. Okay. ונשים לו שם מטה ושלחן וכסא ומנורה. Venassim lo sham
mitah veshulchan vechise u'menorah.
Let's place for him there a bed, a table, a chair, and
a candelabra. אמר אביי ואיתימא רבי יצחק: Amar Abaye ve'itayma Rabbi Yitzchak:
הרוצה ליהנות יהנה כאלישע. Harotzeh lehanot yehaneh ke'Elisha.
If you want to benefit from other people's hospitality, so the good
model would be אלישע. Elisha. You know, somebody provides for you a
bed, a chair, a table, that's the degree that you should allow
yourself to benefit from other people. More than that would be excessive.
ושאינו רוצה ליהנות אל יהנה כשמואל. U'she'eino rotzeh lehanot al yehaneh ke'Shmuel.
And if you don't want to benefit at all from people,
then don't benefit at all, like שמואל Shmuel says. הרמתי. Haramati. שנאמר:
Shenemar: ותשובתו הרמתה כי שם ביתו. U'teshuvato HaRamatah ki sham beito.
He would return to רמתה, Ramatah, that was his house, when שמואל
Shmuel would sort of do a circuit of all of Israel. ואמר
רבי יוחנן: Ve'amar Rabbi Yochanan: שכל מקום שהלך שם ביתו עמו. Shekol
makom shehalach sham beito imo. Wherever he would go, his house was
with him. He'd carry his bed, he'd carry his necessities. He didn't
want to take benefit from anybody. But even if you don't want
to be like שמואל, Shmuel, that's to not sort of benefit from
anybody's hospitality, אלישע Elisha would be the appropriate model. Don't overdo it.
Don't overextend people's hospitality, but the basic necessities. ותאמר אל אישה הנה
נא ידעתי. Vatomer el isha hineh na yadati. This woman, the Shunammite,
said to her husband, "behold I know כי איש אלהים קדוש הוא,"
ki ish elokim kadosh hu, he's a holy man of God. אמר
רבי יוסי בר חנינא: Amar Rabbi Yosei bar Chanina: מכאן שהאשה מכרת
באורחים יותר מן האיש. Mikan sheha'ishah makeret be'orechim yoter min ha'ish. From
here you see that the woman knows, can understand her guests better
than the husband. Also similar to the whole story about מנוח, Manoach,
right? She understood the nature of the angel more than her husband
did. So קדוש הוא, kadosh hu,
he is holy. מנא ידעה? mina yad'ah? Where did she know this?
רב ושמואל. Rav u'Shmuel. חד אמר שלא ראתה זבוב עובר על שלחנו.
Chad amar shelo ra'ata zevuv over al shulchano. There were no flies
around his table. So that's an interesting way of seeing that he's
holy. וחד אמר סדין של פשתן הציעה על מיטתו. Vechad amar sadin
shel pishtan hitzi'ah al mitato. She put on his bed a linen
sheet. ולא ראתה קרי עליו. Velo ra'ata keri alav. And then she
had to do the laundry and there was never any semen on
it, so he never had a nocturnal emission. So he must have
very holy thoughts. It is interesting that one's version of holiness is
again more this metaphysical level, the flies don't even go around him,
and the other... Very sort of practical thing about people and their
sexual thoughts.
Okay. אמר רבי יוסי בר חנינא, Amar Rabi Yossi bar Chanina, הוא
קדוש, hu kadosh, קדוש הוא, kadosh hu, he is holy. הוא קדוש
ומשרתו אינו קדוש, hu kadosh umesharto eino kadosh, he might be holy
but his assistant גיחזי, Geichazi, right remember the stories with גיחזי Geichazi
and אלישע Elisha who took the bribes and so on, גיחזי Geichazi
is not so holy. ויגש גיחזי להדפה, Vayigash Geichazi l'hadpah,
and then it says when she went to try to approach him
and say that her son had died, it says גיחזי Geichazi stepped
forward to push her away. So they make a דרשה derasha on
להדפה, l'hadpah, אמר רבי יוסי בר חנינא Amar Rabi Yossi bar Chanina
שאחז בהוד יפיה. she'achaz behod yafya.
He grabbed her literally the glory of her beauty, which רש״י Rashi
says basically means her breasts, and he does that from להדפה, l'hadpah,
a דרשה derasha on להדפה. l'hadpah. So her servant is not so
holy. עובר עלינו תמיד Over aleinu tamid is constantly passing by us.
אמר רבי יוסי בר חנינא משום רבי אליעזר בן יעקב, Amar Rabi
Yossi bar Chanina mishum Rabi Eliezer ben Yaakov, כל המארח תלמיד חכם
בתוך ביתו, kol hamareach talmid chacham betoch beito,
anybody who hosts a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham in their house, interesting
the shift to תלמיד חכם talmid chacham from a נביא navi but
giving you a little practical meaning, ומהנהו מנכסיו umihanehu minachasav
and allows him to benefit from his property like we saw before
about at least gives him a room and whatever, מעלה עליו הכתוב
כאילו מקריב תמיד, ma'aleh alav hakatuv k'ilu makriv tamid, תמידין, temidin, it
says תמיד, tamid,
it's like you brought sort of regular sacrifices. What exactly is the
comparison is the analogy? I don't know. אמר רבי יוסי בר חנינא
משום רבי אליעזר בן יעקב, Amar Rabi Yossi bar Chanina mishum Rabi
Eliezer ben Yaakov, אל יעמוד אדם במקום גבוה ויתפלל אלא במקום נמוך.
al yaamod adam bemakom gavoah veyitpalel ela bemakom namuch. Okay you know
what I think we will stop here because now we are done
with the אגדתא aggadata and we actually go to turn to some
very practical הלכה halacha of תפילה. tefillah. So what? ומתפלל. umitpalel. We
been there, well we'll get to that. Anyway we'll pick up here
tomorrow.